Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is י"ח *yud-chet*, and
we pick up with,
where do we pick up with, top of י"ח עמוד Amud, א'
*yud-chet amud aleph* about four lines down, מתיבי רב Rav המנונא *mative
rav hamnuna*. We're in the middle of a debate of רב הונא
Rav Huna *Rav Huna* and שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* about when the משנה
Mishna. *mishnah* says יש נדר בתוך נדר neder betoch neder *yesh neder
betoch neder* whether it means that and says, for example, הריני נזיר
הריני נזיר hareini nazir hareini nazir *hareini nazir hareini nazir*, is the
second one work only if it is, according to רב הונא Rav
Huna *Rav Huna*, a requirement not stated in the משנה Mishna *mishnah*,
only if it's a little bit different than the first one. So
הריני נזיר nazir היום *hareini nazir hayom* and then the second one
is הריני נזיר nazir, למחר *hareini nazir lemachar*. And the way the
ר"ן Ran *Ran* explained that is that therefore since there's one day
that they don't overlap, with that one day, אין נזירות nezirot, פחות
משלושים יום *ein nezirut pachos mishloshim yom* comes a whole thirty extra
days. That's רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*. שמואל shmuel *Shmuel* says
no, הריני נזיר nazir הריני נזיר nazir *hareini nazir hareini nazir* like
the simple sense to the משנה Mishna. *mishnah*, that's even if they're
identical, the second one also takes effect, not immediately, it's held in
abeyance until the first one is over and then the second one
takes effect. And what we learned yesterday was that even רב הונא
*Rav Huna* would agree that if somebody said, accepted both of them
at the same time, said like הרי עלי alai, שתי נזירות nezirot
*harei alai shtei nezirut* or something like that, that that actually he
would agree to that phenomenon that one takes effect now and the
other is held in abeyance. His problem is that when one, when
they were sequential and one kicked in first, is it at all
meaningful to accept the second one when there's when you're already exactly
in that same state right now if the second one is identical
to the first one? So that's the debate of רב הונא *Rav
Huna* and שמואל *Shmuel*. And I should mention that the, that there
actually is another approach to this סוגיא sugya. *sugya* that the ר"ן
Ran *Ran* lays out. The way we've been learning it and the
way we'll continue to learn it is that the idea of נדר
בתוך נדר neder betoch neder, *neder betoch neder* is that the second
one sort of is suspended and held in abeyance and the second
נזירות nezirut. *nezirut* will kick in when the first one is finished.
The ר"ן Ran *Ran*, though, however acknowledges that there are those who
read this in a, you know, that basically you're a double נזיר
nazir *nazir* at the same time and that if you would violate
and go ahead and drink grape, drink wine or eat grapes, you
get two sets of lashes. Not exactly clear whether at the end
of it you would bring two sets of קרבנות Korbanot, *korbanot* or
one set of קרבנות Korbanot *korbanot*, but actually understands that the idea
of יש נדר neder בתוך נדר neder *yesh neder betoch neder* is
not the idea that it's held in abeyance and takes effect when
the other one stops, but that actually both take effect at the
same time. As such, it's easier to understand רב הונא *Rav Huna*'s
insistence that they not be the exact same thing. If they're the
exact same thing, it's a principle of אין איסור חל על איסור
issur chal al issur, *ein issur chal al issur*, right? You can't
have one prohibition take effect on top of another. But if they're
slightly different, then these are ideas the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* talks about
in its discussion of אין איסור issur חל chal על איסור issur
*ein issur chal al issur*, like one is an איסור issur מוסיף
*issur mosif* or an איסור issur כולל *issur kolel* to some degree,
it's a different איסור issur *issur* than the then one can take
effect on top of the second one.
So and so that's an approach that the ר"ן Ran *Ran* does
not like, but he acknowledges as a way of reading the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* and perhaps more significantly, according to that approach, it's not
limited to נזירות nezirut. *nezirut*. This approach would say that the example
of נזיר nazir *nazir* in the משנה Mishna *mishnah*, the case of
נזיר nazir *nazir* is just an example, but that actually in principle
if somebody said קונם כיכר זה עלי konam kikar ze alai? קונם
כיכר זה עלי konam kikar ze alai. *konam kikar zeh alai konam
kikar zeh alai*, you know, that actually there would be two איסורים
issurim *issurim* on this loaf of bread and if somebody were to
eat the loaf of bread, he would get two sets of lashes.
Okay, so I wanted to put it out there that the משנה
*mishnah* interestingly says יש נדר neder בתוך נדר neder *yesh neder betoch
neder* but only jumps to a case of נזירות *nezirut* and doesn't
then explain what the significance is that it is does work by
נזירות *nezirut*. So what we've been dealing with is the assumption that
it means that when the first נזירות *nezirut* is over, the second
one kicks in and then we understand why it's unique to נזירות
*nezirut* because only נזירות *nezirut* has sort of like that finite, you
know, time-bound type of nature to it and the second one could
be hovering. But the ר"ן Ran *Ran* does suggest a very different
read that no, you could be a double נזיר nazir *nazir* and
then it wouldn't be limited to נזירות *nezirut*. נזירות *nezirut* would just
be an example and you could actually have somebody that's doubly אסור
assur *assur* with a נדר neder *neder*. This loaf of bread has
two איסורים issurim *issurim* on it, three איסורים Isurim. *issurim* on it,
and that really gets more, much more to classic discussions of איסור
issur, חל chal על איסור issur *issur chal al issur*. Okay, so
that's where we are and that's two very different ways of understanding
where, you know, the סוגיא sugya *sugya*. Now we're going to continue
to work out this debate of רב הונא *Rav Huna* and שמואל
*Shmuel*. Yes, question?
Does שמואל *Shmuel* have a slightly more authoritative edge as the type
of transition from תנא *tanna* to אמורא *amora* in that from problem
of שמואל *Shmuel* and רב הונא *Rav Huna*?
Like I find that. Yeah, yeah, it is true, you know, I
don't know in terms of like, you know, the issues of פסק
*psak*, it's always very confusing because on the one hand you're supposed
to say הלכתא כבתרא *hilchata kebatra* which gives weight to the later
opinion, but then there's the idea that no, like the earlier opinions
are like, you know, somehow more authoritative and like אין הלכה halacha
כתלמיד במקום הרב *ein halacha ketalmid b'makom harav* and so, you know,
it's never exactly black and white about that. Alright, so let's take
a look. Now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* continues, okay? מתיבי רב המנונא
*mative rav
hamnuna*. A nazir to to be to separate, מכאן *mikan*, so then
it's double language נזיר nazir, להזיר *nazir l'hazir*, שנזירות חלה על נזירות
*shenezirut chala al nezirut*, that you can have a double nezirut, שיחול
*sheyachol*, a nezirut on top of another one. והלא דין din הוא
*vehalo din hu*, because you could have made a קל וחומר kal
vachomer. *kal vachomer* the other way, and you could have said the
following: מה שבועה shvua חמורה *ma shvua chamura*, שבועה shvua, *shvua* is
weightier and we'll discuss in a minute why שבועה shvua *shvua* is
considered weightier, אין שבועה חלה על שבועה ein shvua chala al shvua.
*ein shvua chala al shvua*, you can't have a שבועה shvua *shvua*
on a שבועה shvua. *shvua*, right, if you took a שבועה shvua
*shvua* not to eat a loaf of bread and then took another
שבועה shvua *shvua*, you would say it's, right, that it does not
take effect because you're already מושבע ועומד mushbah ve'omed, *mushba v'omed*, you
already are obligated to do it, so it doesn't make sense to
obligate yourself again. Okay, so מה שבועה shvua חמורה שאין שבועה חלה
על שבועה shvua chala al shvua *ma shvua chamura she'ein shvua chala
al shvua*,
so נזירות קלה לא כל שכן *nezirut kala lo kol sheken*, how
much more so that the lighter issue of נזירות *nezirut* you should
say should not be able to double up? So that's what you
would have thought. תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, alright anyway, we'll see, תלמוד
לומר נזיר nazir להזיר *talmud lomar nazir l'hazir*, the double language. מכאן
שנזירות חלה על נזירות *mikan shenezirut chala al nezirut*. Okay, so that
just tells you it once takes effect on the other. So how
is this going to play into the debate? היכי דמי *heichi dami*,
what's the case? אילימא דאמר הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר למחר *eileima
d'amar hareini nazir hayom hareini nazir l'machar*, if it's Rav Huna's case
that I'm a נזיר *nazir* today, I'm a נזיר *nazir* tomorrow, הקרא
בעי *hakra ba'ei*, why would you need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? Of
course that the second one should take effect. Since there's one day
that they don't overlap, again this is the way the Ran reads
it, since there's one day they don't overlap, that day, that day
31, the second נזירות *nezirut* will take effect and then it'll bring
everything with it. You shouldn't need a פסוק *pasuk* for that, that's
just logical. אלא לאו דאמר הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר היום *ela
lav d'amar hareini nazir hayom hareini nazir hayom*, it must be you
said the exact same thing. I'm a נזיר *nazir* today, and then
you said again, I'm a נזיר *nazir* today. So that the second
one is exactly coincides with the first one. וקתני נזירות חלה על
נזירות *v'katani nezirut chala al nezirut*, it takes effect. So the fact
that you need a פסוק *pasuk* shows we're talking about a case
that's not obvious, and therefore it must be this case that there
are two identical neziresses and nevertheless it works. So that's a proof
against Rav Huna. It says לא *lo*, not necessarily. הכא במאי עסקינן
כגון שקיבל עליו שתי נזירויות בבת אחת kigon she-kibal alav shtei nezirot
bat achat. *hacha b'mai askinan k'gon shekibel alav shtei neziruyot b'vat achat*.
No, here's another example that you accepted two neziresses at once, and
that's not obvious because since they're both the same, you know, the
exact same length of time, there's no time where the second one
is effective when the, you know, is effective when the first one
is not. Based, you know, you're saying I right now accept on
myself two neziresses to start today. So that's not obvious that the
second one should be meaningful, right, because the second one has no
time that it doesn't overlap with the first. And nevertheless the פסוק
*pasuk* comes along and teaches you that the second one is there,
it's held in abeyance, and it will take effect when the first
one finishes. That's what you need a פסוק *pasuk* for. That's very
different than when there's actually a period of non-overlap.
Nevertheless, so why does Rav Huna agree to it? Because as we've
said before, Rav Huna does say when you accept them both at
the same time, then you, he accepts the idea of this phenomenon
that one takes effect and one is hovering. His only problem is
not that that phenomenon could exist, his only problem is if you
started with one in effect, then the attempt to accept upon yourself
a second one is a meaningless attempt. Right you can't do it
once you already have that state, you cannot try to put a
state upon that. But if you try, created that whole package together,
right, two at one time, which meant one took effect and one
was hovering, that you're able to do. But if one's already there,
then it's like you can't go ahead and try to change the
state of something if it's already, if it already has exactly that
same state in effect. Okay, so when you do say though two
at once, that's not so obvious it would work, that's the case
Rav Huna does agree to that does work, and that's what the
פסוק *pasuk* is coming to teach you that when you do that
it does work and the second one is held in abeyance. And
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just to wrap this up says ומאי
חומרא דשבועה *umai chumra d'shvua*, and what way is a שבועה shvua
*shvua* more strict that it was like that I would have said
well, it doesn't work by a שבועה shvua *shvua*, it certainly should
work by נזירות *nezirut*? ממאי *memai*? אילימא משום דחיילא אפילו על דבר
שאין בו ממש *eileima mishum d'chaila afilu al davar she'ein bo mamash*,
if it's because a שבועה shvua *shvua* takes effect on something that
is not physical, right, it obligates you to do an action, it's
not about an object? נדר neder נמי חמיר *neder nami chamir*, there's
a way in which נדר neder *neder* is weightier, שכן חל chal,
על מצווה כרשות *sheken chal al mitzva k'reshut*, it takes effect on
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* objects and it prevents you from doing a מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* like when you forbid all סוכות *sukkot* on you or
all תפילין *tefillin* on you, right, and a שבועה shvua *shvua* can't
do that because a שבועה shvua *shvua* directly contradicts your obligation where
this does more of an end-run around it. So there's ways in
which שבועה shvua *shvua* is weightier, there's ways in which נדר neder
*neder* is weightier. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא משום דכתיב
בה בשבועה לא ינקה *ela mishum d'chtiv ba bishvua lo yenake*, because
by a שבועה shvua, *shvua* it says כי לא ינקה השם lo
yenakeh Hashem, את אשר ישא שמו לשוא *ki lo yenake Hashem et
asher yisa shemo lashav*. So since there's this idea that שבועה shvua,
*shvua*, God does not cleanse the person, this really is an idea
of weightier. It's not like a technical way in some ways in
which שבועה shvua *shvua* works and נדר neder *neder* doesn't work and
vice versa. That more has to do with like the technical formal
nature of what is the scope of שבועה shvua *shvua*, what is
the scope of נדר neder? *neder*. Here it really is in terms
of weighty, a שבועה shvua *shvua* is about God's name and about
taking God's name in vain, and therefore the violation of a שבועה
shvua *shvua*, the weight of the prohibition of a שבועה shvua is
much weightier. Now why that weightier should translate into this idea of
can you double up a שבועה shvua and double up a נדר
neder, that I have no idea. Okay, but anyway in some formal
sense it was saying it doesn't work by שבועה, shvua. my default
assumption would have been it doesn't work by נדר neder or by
נזיר and the פסוק comes to teach me that it does. One
last point though which is and you know something more to discuss
well we're not going to get to שבועות Shvuot for a while
is that פסוק לא ינקה, pasuk lo yenakeh, if you look at
this little תוספות, Tosafot, דהא דמשום דכתיב לא ינקה כדאמרינן בשבועות, deha
d'mishum dechtiv lo yenakeh k'damrinan b'Shvuot, והתם איכא חומרות אחרינות והכא נקט
הפשוטות. v'hatam ika chumrot achrinot v'hacha nakat hapshutot. There are other ways
in which שבועה shvua is more חמור, chamor, here just takes the
simple way דכתיב בקרא דלא תשא. dechtiv bikra d'lo tisa. ואף על
גב דלא ינקה בשבועת שקר כתיב v'af al gav d'lo yenakeh b'shvuat
sheker ktiv ומתניתין מיירי בשבועת ביטוי, umitnitin mairi b'shvuat bituy, מכל מקום
חומרא חשיבותא שוה היא. mikol makom chumra chashivuta shava hi.
So he says there's a little difference. The פסוק לא ינקה השם
pasuk lo yenakeh Hashem is by a שבועת שקר, shvuat sheker, which
means a שבועה shvua, of the past. You take an oath in
the name of God I never did X, Y, and Z. In
the name of God I did the following. Okay, there you're actually
calling God to testify to the truth of your statement and to
bear witness and you're lying. That's the real לא ינקה השם את
אשר ישא את שמו לשוא. lo yenakeh Hashem et asher yisa et
shemo lashav. That's called a שבועת שקר shvuat sheker about the past.
A שבועת ביטוי shvuat bituy in a way it's similar to a
שבועת שקר, shvuat sheker, but it's really, and we discussed this the
other day, it creates an obligation. I take an oath that I
will go ahead and go out with movies to you tomorrow. Okay,
so now what that does is that creates an obligation upon me
to go out with the movies. Although you could have said no,
then when you don't go to the movies with the guy tomorrow,
retroactively you have called God to bear witness over something that was
false and to back up your word and it's the same idea
of a שקר, sheker, it's just a שקר sheker retroactively is a
שקר sheker because you didn't do what you said you would do.
Okay, but that's not so much how we conceptualize it. We conceptualize
it more that when you take an oath to do something, it
creates an obligation to do something. And that's part of the idea
of אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. ein shvua chala al shvua, Right?
If you're already obligated, you can't obligate yourself again. It doesn't focus
it on using God's name anymore, it focuses more on the obligation
created as a result of the שבועה. shvua So the תוספות Tosafot
is saying so it's not exactly the same idea of לא ינקה
השם, but nevertheless in the category, שבועה shvua as a category is
much weightier than נדר neder, and that's the structure of the קל
וחומר. kal vachomer Yes.
תוספות Tosafot says a few things. One, sort of even though there's
difference, it seems to me the authority of God is what's behind
or grounding the obligation.
Right. Right.
I'm missing something really, really basic I think. In the קל וחומר
kal vachomer you start with the קל kal and you argue to
the חמור. chamor. Right. But here you're starting, what kind of argument
is this? Like because it's not, it's not חל by שבועה shvua
which is more חמור, chamor, of course it's not חל on נדר
neder, which is קל. kal. That doesn't make sense.
Here's the choice, it makes sense which way you're going. If you're
trying to argue that you should have a שבועה shvua חלה על
שבועה chala al shvua. based on the fact that it works by
a נזיר, that would be the קל וחומר kal vachomer structure you're
saying. If a נדר neder is, if נדר חל על נדר neder
chal al neder as we find by a נזיר which is קל,
kal, then שבועה shvua which is חמור, chamor, קל וחומר kal vachomer,
we should say שבועה shvua should be חלה על שבועה. shvua That's
what you wanted to say. Here we're doing the same thing except
we're doing the counterfactual.
If it doesn't work by a שבועה shvua which is חמור, chamor,
then it certainly shouldn't work by a נזיר which is קל. kal.
It's the same idea, it's just the counterfactual. Because think of it
this way, if it did work by a נזיר which was קל,
kal, then why doesn't it work by a שבועה shevuah, which is
חמור? chamor?
That's your קל וחומר, kal vachomer right? So since the קל וחומר
kal vachomer logic would say if it works by נזיר which is
קל, kal, it should work by שבועה shevuah, which is חמור, chamor,
but we know it doesn't work by שבועה shevuah which is חמור,
chamor, so then that logic should necessitate that it can't work by
נזיר which is קל. kal. So it's the lack of thing, you
know, it's sort of like if P then Q. We did that
before when we had מכל שכן mikol sheken or השתא. hashta. I
mean whatever. Okay. So say if not Q then not P. Right?
If the קל וחומר kal vachomer, is... I'll just draw all of
this. We have a little Jewish history up here on the board.
Okay, I don't know.
We say if P then Q, if this is the קל, kal,
if something is true by the קל, kal, certainly it should be
true by the חמור, chamor, right? So that's your קל kal וחומר,
right? If something is true by a קל kal. it should certainly
be true by the חמור. chamor. So the logic flip of this
is if not Q then not P. If it's not true by
the thing that's חמור, chamor, it certainly shouldn't be true by the
thing that's קל. kal. So if שבועה shevuah, which is חמור, chamor,
אין שבועה חלה על שבועה, ein shvuah chala al shvuah, then it
certainly should say אין נדר חל על נדר ein neder chal al
neder by a נדר neder, which is קל. Okay, so it is
the same, it's just the flip side of it. All right. See
that. All right.
See that propositional logic that we learned in high school or college
comes to be... anyway, so moving on in the גמרא. Gemara So
anyway, that's the end of the סוגיא. sugya It's not clear whether
we come out like רב or רב הונא or שמואל about whether
you need the second one when it's going to take effect by
נזיר to be slightly different than the first, like to take effect
a day later.
Even רב הונא though does agree that the problem is that one
is preexisting. existing,
and if you were to accept both of them at the same
time, he would agree that it would take effect. And again to
remind you, this idea that the ר"ן Ran has been reading the
whole סוגיא that the second one is hovering, waiting to take effect,
but he acknowledges that there's a read of the סוגיא that's much
more like a classic איסור חל על איסור, which is that they
might both take effect at the same time and you might doubly
transgress. And according to that, it could in theory work even by
a נדר neder and not just by a נזיר, and something could
be doubly forbidden. Okay, yeah.
Did you want to say something else? Yeah, sure. Is there something
that's bothering me since all of this is about the seriousness of
speech acts? Right. So in the spirit of שמור וזכור בדיבור אחד,
shamor vezachor bedibur echad, you can never say two speech acts simultaneously.
They're always sequential, even if it's only a microsecond.
No, no, no. That's if you said two sentences. But let's say
you said, I now accept upon myself two נזירויות nezirot beginning today.
No, but I'm talking
about, that's what בבת אחת bevat achat means.
I understand that, but wait a second. You have here, you
know, הריני עליכם הרי מהיום אסור מהיום hareini aleichem harei mehayom assur
mehayom and then you say the same thing again.
Right, that's exactly what we're discussing.
Yeah, but it's not, but you're not saying those two things at
the same time.
I know. So when רב הונא agrees when it's at the same
time, he doesn't mean that the two sentences are said at the
same time. He means you said one sentence accepting both of them
as one. You said one sentence and you said
הרי עלי שתי נזירויות harei alai shtei nezirot from today. That's what,
so בבת אחת, bevat achat, does that mean you said הריני נזיר
הריני נזיר בבת אחת? bevat achat? It means you accepted both of
them in one sentence.
Right, I understand, but when you say those two sentences, you should
never ever be able to say that they're anything other than sequential,
one builds one...
Which is correct. We're not disagreeing. That's correct. Okay. All right. Now,
I want to say before we go on another very important and
interesting discussion that the ר"ן Ran. has based on ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. And
he says like, look, we've talked about נדר neder בתוך נדר neder,
and שבועה בתוך שבועה. shvua betoch shvua. What about a נדר neder
and a שבועה, shevuah a נדר neder following a שבועה, shevuah a
שבועה shevuah, following a נדר? neder, Somebody says שבועה
שלא אוכל כיכר זה shvua shelo ochal kikar ze and then he
says כיכר זה קונם עלי. kikar ze konam alai. Okay, or he
says כיכר זה קונם עלי kikar ze konam alai and then he
says שבועה שלא אוכל כיכר זה. shvua shelo ochal kikar ze. Is
the second one take effect or not? All right, so he said,
hear the question, right? Assuming you don't have a שבועה בתוך שבועה
shvua betoch shvua and you don't have a נדר neder בתוך נדר,
neder the only exception would let's say be נזירות, right? נזירות is
the only exception. Normally you can't double up. Something already has a
state, you can't impose the same state upon it. So what if
I said שבועה שלא אוכל כיכר זה shvua shelo ochal kikar ze
and then I said קונם כיכר זה עלי? konam kikar ze alai,
So the ר"ן Ran. says that works. Why does that work? Because
similar to he says if I have a מצוה to sit in
a סוכה, sukkah, I could still make the סוכה sukkah forbidden to
me, right? So the idea is that the personal obligation and the
objects don't work at the same plane, they don't are not seen
as contradicting. So if I said instead of saying I have a
מצוה to sit in a סוכה sukkah and then I say the
סוכה sukkah is forbidden which works, let's say I said שבועה shvuah
I will eat this כיכר kikar and then I said קונם כיכר
זה עלי. konam kikar ze alai So the effect of it will
be that that'll cause me to transgress one of those, but the
actual act of making the bread forbidden is not directly confronting my
personal obligation to eat the loaf of bread, right? It's one thing
is talking about the object, and another thing is talking about me.
The reality will be that I won't be able to do both
of them. But he says that's no different than saying I have
an obligation to sit in a סוכה sukkah and then I say
קונם כל סוכות עלי, konam kol sukkot alai, okay, which yes you
will wind up subverting, you know, one of those two things, one
of those two things you won't be able to do. But the
reality is that since they're not talking to one another, okay,
then one can take effect even though when now they come in
conversation there's going to be a conflict. So if somebody said שבועה
shvuah, I'll eat this loaf of bread then קונם כיכר זה konam
kikar zeh עלי, alay. he said that's no different than the סוכה
sukkah case, and it takes effect. And certainly if what you're doing
is reinforcing your obligation, you say שבועה shvuah, I won't eat this
loaf of bread and then you said קונם konam this loaf of
bread עלי, again it's not like oh you're doubling up, they're not
in conversation, they do take effect. That's all very nice and lovely.
But then he says something that's a little, a
little counter-intuitive, which is he says if you reverse it, it won't
work. Let's say you said קונם כיכר זה konam kikar zeh, עלי
and then you said שבועה shvuah. that I'll eat this loaf of
bread or שבועה shvuah, I won't eat this loaf of bread. He
says that doesn't work. Why not? Don't we assume that you know
they're not in conversation, one thing is talking about the object, the
other thing is talking about your personal responsibility? So when you accept
a personal responsibility to eat this loaf of bread that you made
forbidden, it's not relating to the bread, it's just about you. You
know why don't we just say again they're in different conversations and
therefore this can take effect even though the loaf of bread is
already forbidden? And then he says no that's not true, because when
the loaf of bread is forbidden it's like, you know, its status
of forbidden also is not just like an איסור חפצא, issur cheftza,
it's not just the thing is forbidden. The implication of it being
forbidden is that you're forbidden to eat it, right? It's sort of
like if a tree falls in a forest doesn't make a sound
right, and then nobody hears it, has it made a sound? If
a loaf of bread is forbidden and no people live on the...
If a loaf of bread is forbidden and no people live on
the world, right, you know, you know, like if it's forbidden, you
know, then is it really forbidden? Forbidden, right, so somehow when I
say, this is interesting, if I say I won't eat this loaf
of bread, that doesn't have to say something that there's a status
about the loaf of bread. The loaf of bread could be neutral
and I still won't eat it, right? There's nothing wrong with the
loaf, it's not about you, it's about me, right? There's nothing wrong
with the loaf of bread. I am choosing not to eat it,
okay? And that so therefore when I say I won't eat it,
the status is neutral. Then I want to say no, I'm going
to make it forbidden, right, that's doing something different than my שבועה.
shvuah My שבועה shvuah doesn't say anything about the status. So I
can start with my שבועה, shvuah and then I can say something
about the status either to reinforce the שבועה shvuah or even that
will effectively counteract countermand the שבועה shvuah because my שבועה does not
make a statement about the status of the loaf of bread. Whereas
the status of the loaf of bread does make a statement about
me. If the status is that this may not be eaten, then
it is actually making a statement and that statement is, me, Dov
Linzer, is not allowed to eat or me anybody to whom this
status relates is not allowed to eat that loaf. So already implicit
in that statement is my personal obligation and responsibility. So if I
start with the idea that this loaf is forbidden and then I
say I take a שבועה I won't eat the loaf, it's לא
חל lo chal because I'm already not able to eat it because
that status already said something about me, okay, about me, my obligation
or and certainly if I say that it's forbidden and then I
take a שבועה I will eat it, it's לא חל lo chal
because I already have a responsibility not to eat it. So it
איסור חפצא issur cheftza says the ר"ן Ran very interesting conceptually
also results in an איסור גברא issur gavra because the status says
something about you, right, if it can't be eaten it means certain
acts you're not allowed to do to it, right, whereas my איסור
גברא issur gavra if I'm obligated to eat or not obligated or
obligated not to eat does not say that I recognize some special
status about the thing, it just talks just about what I will
do. So very interesting that the order matters and he gives the
example and we'll take the questions, he gives the example about this
from from like תורה Torah statuses, right? When you say and people
ask this when they're first introduced to this idea of איסור גברא,
issur gavra, איסור חפצא. issur cheftza. Like let's say you say חזיר.
chazir. Is חזיר chazir an איסור גברא issur gavra or an איסור
חפצא? issur cheftza? So our intuition about it is, I mean it's
an איסור חפצא, issur cheftza, there's something intrinsically problematic with pork, right?
We think like it's not just that the תורה Torah just you
know that's at least our religious like intuitive response whether it's הלכתי
halakhic or not, right? But this is but you know what does
that mean? Like I mean it's only אסור assur cause the תורה
Torah told you not to eat it and the language in the
תורה Torah doesn't say pork shall not be eaten, it says you
shall not eat it. I mean it actually does sometimes say shall
not be eaten, okay, but anyway לא יאכלו lo ye'akhelu
but okay you can maybe try to be מדייק medayek by the
grammar but nevertheless you know you could say the תורה Torah is
prohibiting me to eat it. It's not somehow saying that this thing
is forbidden, right? So there are actually some that say that every
איסור in the תורה Torah is an איסור גברא. issur gavra. There's
no such thing as an איסור חפצא issur cheftza in the תורה
Torah because everything is what you are not allowed to do. You
can't eat it, right? So but what the ר"ן ran is saying
is that no that the תורה Torah might be saying this thing
is intrinsically problematic has the status of we would call מאכלות אסורות
ma'akhalot assurot or in the vernacular טריף treif which says something about
how we think about the nature of the thing. But the implication
of that nature is therefore I may there's always the therefore. Therefore
because this is טריף treif therefore I may not eat it. Okay
it sort of starts with the status, not just like no it's
totally okay it's whatever but you know you're no but but you
know but but you know you personally don't eat this completely neutral
object. Most of the things start with the idea no it's a
problematic object and has the and therefore but it ends with therefore
you don't eat it. So it איסור חפצא issur cheftza results in
an איסור גברא issur gavra and it really packages both. So if
I start with an איסור חפצא issur cheftza the therefore I don't
eat it, therefore I can't take a שבועה upon that because it
resulted in telling me something about what I am and not allowed
to do. But if I start with a שבועה then the object
is in itself completely neutral and then even though I have a
שבועה I can now do something to change the status of the
object. So let's just read that in the ר"ן ran it's a
very important conceptual idea and then if there's questions I'll take questions.
So if you go here sixth
line down from the ראש Rosh in the ר"ן.
Ran Oh you found it already.
So it says כי נדרא חייל על שבועה ואין השבועות חלות על
הנדר.
Ki
nedara
chal al shvua v'ein hashvuot chalot al haneder. Right.
So I want to read the key line. Hold on. It's right
by the הלכות.
halachot. Yeah yeah
yeah yeah.
גירסא girsa in the ר"ן. Yeah I know. I know. I just
want to get a little bit into it. I don't want to
read the whole thing. One minute.
Let's start from ולקלה למימר. vulekala lemeimar. Do you see the line
above the הגהות הב"ח hagahos ha-bach in the left? So the line,
it's like a line above, the line that starts with the word
איסור
and go in the middle of the line where it says ולקלה
למימר. vulekala lemeimar. Do
people have that? Beginning of the line is the word נשבע. nishba.
All right, right. Okay. ולקלה למימר דכי היכי דאיסור חפצא דנדרים חייל
על איסור גברא דשבועות.
vulekala lemeimar dechi heichi de-issur
cheftza de-nedarim chail al issur gavra de-shevuos.
The same way once you have an איסור גברא issur gavra on
yourself, you can still go ahead and then make the object forbidden,
you know, and that's not doubling up. הכא נמי איסור גברא דשבועות
ליחול על איסור חפצא דנדרים. hacha nami issur gavra de-shevuos leichol al
issur cheftza de-nedarim. That means if you start with an איסור חפצא,
issur cheftza, the loaf of bread is forbidden, then you should also
be able to say, and now I'm forbidden to eat it. You
can't say that. משום דבנדרים כי היכי דאיתיה איסור חפצא, mishum de-vinedarim
ke-heichi de-ishei issur cheftza,
although נדרים nedarim starts with an איסור חפצא, issur cheftza, makes the
loaf forbidden, איסור גברא נמי אית ביה. issur gavra nami is beih.
It also translates into telling you something, saying something about you and
your obligations. שהרי מכיון שנאסר עליו, sheharei mikeivan shene'esar alav,
once the loaf of bread is forbidden, חייל עליה בלא יחל דברו.
chail aleih belo yachel devaro. Then the הלכה is you're not allowed
to violate. So that status translates into your
obligation. והאי לאו איסור גברא הוא. ve-hai lav issur gavra hu. והאי
לאו, ve-hai lav, excuse me, that negative prohibition איסור גברא הוא issur
gavra hu is something saying it to you as a person. ככל
לא תעשה שבתורה, kechol lo sa'aseh sheba-torah,
like any negative prohibition in the תורה, torah, which why I read
it is he's not just telling you there's a לא תעשה, lo
sa'aseh, but he's telling you everything in the תורה torah is an
איסור גברא. issur gavra. Don't do this, right? Every one of the
365 לא תעשה lo sa'asehs is telling you what you may not
do. But we can still say that something like, I don't know,
חזיר chazir or מעילה me'ilah or these types of things are איסור
חפצא issur cheftza because they start with the idea that this object
is as a problematic prohibited status, but the translation is, and therefore
you don't eat it. So any איסור חפצא issur cheftza comes with
an איסור גברא. issur gavra. הלכך אין מקום לשבועה שתחול על נדרים.
hilkach ein makom lishevuah shetachol al nedarim.
So it can't take place once if you start with a נדר,
neder you can't add on it a שבועה, because a נדר neder
translates into an איסור גברא. issur gavra. An איסור גברא issur gavra
doesn't translate into an איסור חפצא. issur cheftza. והכי איתא בירושלמי פרק
קמא דמכילתין, ve-hachi issa b'Yerushalmi perek kama de-mechilten, and this is in
the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, בכיכר אחד מכיון שהזכיר עליו שבועה כנבלה הוא. bekikar
echad mikeivan shehizkir alav shevuah keneveilah hu. Once you say a שבועה,
which really means a נדר, nadar, you made it like a נבלה.
neveilah. מכאן ואילך, mikan va'eilach, if then you were to try to
make it prohibited again, כמי שחל שבועה על איסורין ואין שבועה חלה
על איסורין. kemi shechal shevuah al issurin ve-ein shevuah chala al issurin.
Once it's אסור assur as a נדר, nadar, you cannot make a
שבועה on top of it. אמר רב יודן, amar Rav Yudan, והוא
שהזכיר נדר ואחר כך הזכיר שבועה. vehu shehizkir neder ve-achar kach hizkir
shevuah. If you started with a נדר neder. and then you said
a שבועה, the שבועה wouldn't take effect because the נדר, nadar which
affected the status, also said something about you and what you are
and are not allowed to do. אבל אם הזכיר שבועה ואחר כך
נדר, aval im hizkir shevuah ve-achar kach neder, but if you started
with saying a שבועה you won't eat it, and then you made
a נדר neder that it was forbidden, הנדרים חלים על האיסורין. ha-nedarim
chalim al ha-issurin.
The נדר can take effect because your איסור not to eat it
doesn't say something about its status. So your status can still, you
can now, now go ahead and and change its status if you
started with your obligation. But if you started with its status, its
status translated into your obligation and therefore you can't double up then.
Yes.
So by הקדש, hekdesh, it's the same principle except it it
it conflates that distinction because if I'm מקדיש makdish something, it's also
אסור assur to you.
Right, well that's exactly the Ran's point. That's an איסור חפצא issur
cheftza that then translates into an איסור גברא. issur gavra. Every איסור
חפצא issur cheftza translates into an איסור גברא. issur gavra. Right?
No, but I'm saying, yes, but in this case the איסור חפצא
issur cheftza translates into the איסור גברא issur gavra just for that
one individual. Yes, making the, right, or could, right, correct, correct. I
have the power to translate that איסור חפצא issur cheftza into an
איסור גברא issur gavra for you.
Right, that is correct. I mean, you, yeah, I mean, that's true,
that is correct. I mean, that's true also by a נדר, you
don't have to be הקדש, hekdesh, it can be making a נדר
אסור assur. to everybody. But yes, correct.
Right, that's intrinsic to the nature of קדושה. kedusha. Exactly, exactly.
I mean, look, you imagine it like, let's say there is a
there's a a zone of like, you know, I don't know, like,
you know, whatever, power plant, like danger, you know, high voltage, nobody
can come in or whatever, right? That starts as an איסור חפצא,
issur cheftza, right? This place is very dangerous, but it translates into
like nobody's allowed to go in here. However, if you say to
your kid, like, stay out of this room, I'm here now, whatever,
there's no איסור חפצא issur cheftza with the room. It's just something
about that person and where they're allowed to be. Right? So but
every, so so something about what you tell to a particular person
or even to everybody in the world doesn't necessarily mean that there's
something problematic about that space or that thing or whatever. It's just,
whereas if something starts with the thing problematic, it translates into and
therefore nobody can do anything, it translates into an איסור גברא. issur
gavra. Yes, you had a question, חיים? Chaim? No?
And the לא תעשה lo sa'aseh is what do we say?
לא תעשה lo sa'aseh is in the תורה. torah. So that's what
I said. There are some that want to say that every איסור
in the תורה torah is an איסור גברא issur gavra because it
always tells you what to do. But what the Ran is saying
is you don't have to say that because the לא תעשה lo
sa'aseh is in the תורה, torah, some of them at least. can
be איסור חפצא, issur cheftza, right? But איסור חפצא issur cheftza doesn't
stop at איסור חפצא. issur cheftza. The תורה Torah isn't just telling
you you should know there's something out there called חזיר chazir which
is deeply problematic to your metaphysical soul. No, it's not telling you
that. It might start by saying something about the object, but then
it translates it into and therefore you may not eat it. So
it is true that every לא תעשה lo ta'aseh in the תורה
Torah is an איסור גברא, issur gavra, but it doesn't mean it's
only an איסור גברא. issur gavra. Based on what the רן is
saying is it could, some of them could start with an איסור
חפצא. issur cheftza.
So it depends on the law?
Well, you have to, right, then that's an interesting question. See, the
whole מסכת נדרים masechet nedarim introduces, I mean, the Briskers love מסכת
נדרים masechet nedarim because the most paradigmatic
לומדות lomdus concept of the Briskers or primary רב חיים rav chaim
Brisker sort of introduced was the idea of גברא gavra or חפצא.
cheftza. If you say that something is an obligation, a status, or
whatever, are you talking about the status of the object or the
obligation on the person? Okay, is this דין being said? Well,
okay, I'm not sure where you're going with that, but hold on.
Anyway, so, but, but
the point is that this is basically the discourse in נדרים nedarim
where it's the difference between a נדר and a שבועה, but the
fact that it focuses us on to whom is the status being
applied, right, that then can be a question you can ask in
other things that have nothing to do with נדר, right? How much
does, like I said before, like the whole idea of לא יאכל,
lo ye'achel, shall not be eaten, as opposed to it says לא
תאכלו? lo to'chelu? One focuses on you, one focuses on the object,
and there are implications, like maybe that's why some things are אסור
בהנאה assur behana'ah and other things are only אסור באכילה assur beachilah
because איסור הנאה issur hana'ah has a more of a sense of
complete hands-off, which reflects something more deeply problematic about the identity and
the status of the object, whereas an איסור אכילה issur achilah is
less completely that this thing is completely objectionable, it's just more about
the action that you may or may not do with it, right?
So anyway, this leads to that whole, to that whole collection of
terms, of concepts that can be applied elsewhere. So while for נדרים
nedarim purposes we don't care about whether איסורים of the תורה Torah
are חפצא cheftza or גברא, gavra, what we really are concerned about
is whether it's דבר הנדור davar hanadur or לא דבר הנדור, lo
davar hanadur, right? That's the issue. If we want to use other
איסורים in the תורה, Torah, we want to ask are they a
דבר הנדור davar hanadur or not? But when we think about איסורים
שבתורה, issurim shebatorah, we want to ask, right, is this something that
the thing itself is basically fundamentally neutral and the תורה Torah is
still telling me not to do it? Or does it start with
some problematic status about the object itself? I'll give you one example.
We're learning this year about, I mean again, it fundamentally starts as
a conceptual framing. What might that lead to in terms of thinking
about practical implications, but it's a way of thinking about the issue.
The תורה Torah says don't cook meat and milk and it says
don't eat
meat and milk. How do you understand the relationship of that? So,
some want to say, well, the real איסור of the תורה Torah
is not to eat meat and milk, but it so wanted to
protect you from eating meat and milk it said don't even like
cook it or whatever lest you come to eat it, like a
גזירה gezeirah in the תורה. Torah. Okay, that focuses on the action
and on everything else that results is just to protect me from
doing that action and it focuses on the איסור גברא issur gavra
if you would or on the action or on the person. Whereas
the other approach is, no, the very phenomenon of meat and milk
cooked together is intrinsically a problematic phenomenon, it's a type of a
כלאיים, kilayim, of a שעטנז, shatnez, it's intrinsically problematic. And therefore I'm
not allowed to create it, and since I'm not allowed to create
it, I'm also like when it exists I'm not allowed to benefit
from it, I'm not allowed to eat from it. This whole thing
is fundamentally problematic and that leads to a whole series of prohibitions
that result from this phenomenon of meat and milk. So it's a
question of what your orientation is. Do you start with the person
or do you start with the object or do you start with
the action? Yes, Jonathan.
I don't, I can't quite work this out, I'm not sure I
understand. A נדר isn't,
the לשון lashon of a נדר is not made in a vacuum.
You make a נדר for yourself. Right.
You say קונם כיכר זו עלי.
konam
kikar zu alay.
עלי. Right.
Or
you could say קונם כיכר זה konam kikar zeh, and then presumably
it's on everyone if it's your loaf of bread.
It's a personal statement.
Ah, you could say קונם כיכר זה, or כיכר זה קונם kikar
zeh konam and if it's your loaf of bread it would mean
on everyone.
That's why you're not allowed to prohibit something that's
somebody else's thing on everyone but your thing on everyone. Right.
Whereas the תורה, Torah, when you use that expression לא יאכל, lo
ye'achel, right, where, it's,
it seems powerful to me in the sense that we're not translating
it as 'it shall not be eaten', it's really being translated as
you משה, moshe, you יענקי, yanky, you שמואל shall not eat this.
Well, but that's the רן's point.
He's saying it starts with 'it shall not be
eaten', but then the translation of 'it shall not be eaten' is
'all of you are prohibited to eat from it'. Right.
It's speaking directly to each individual, each שומר מצוות, shomer mitzvos, it's
speaking directly to them. It's not, so it's like the נדר being
made in a vacuum and then being personalized.
Well, that's what the רן says happens by נדרים. nedarim. You start
by saying קונם כיכר זה, and then the תורה Torah says okay.
Exactly. Yeah, exactly. Alright, so now let's go on. So the גמרא
Gemara says
like this. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Okay, so now שבועה שלא אוכל
ואכל אינו חייב אלא אחת. shvuah she'lo ochal v'achal eino chayav ela
achat.
So this is, we're back to the גמרא, last third. So if
somebody makes a שבועה on a שבועה, it's not חל, okay? And
he transgresses, he only transgresses once. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so now we're going to revisit something we saw yesterday. נשאל על
ראשונה שנייה חלה עליו. Nish'al al rishona, shniya chala alav.
If the person actually, he's got a היתר שבועה heter shvuah like
a היתר נדרים heter nedarim on the first שבועה, then the second
one kicks in. Although the second one was meaningless at the time
because you were already מושבע mushbah, ועומד, right? שבועה שלא אוכל, shvuah
she'lo ochal, then you already מושבע, mushbah, then you said שבועה שלא
אוכל, shvuah she'lo ochal, the second one meant nothing. But retroactively, if
you erase the first one, then the, then retroactively the second one
can, can have been meaningful. Okay, ממי? Mi-mai? How do you know
that? Maybe if it wasn't meaningful at the time, it was a
meaningless statement period. דלא קתני אינו אלא אחת. De-lo katani eino ela
achat. It doesn't say if you say the two of them, it's
only one. It says קתני אינו חייב אלא אחת, Katani eino chayav
ela achat, which means that you're not חייב chayav for the second
one, but to some degree the second one is still there. There
is still this idea again like of this hovering idea even by
a שבועה. קתני אינו חייב אלא אחת. Katani eino chayav ela achat.
רווחא הוא דלית ליה. Revacha hu de-leit lei. It doesn't have any
space to take effect. Okay, it doesn't have any opening. כי מדשאל
ליה, Ki midshal lei, but when you ask on it, when you,
then חברתה חיילא, chaverta chayla,
then the, the friend will kick in. The other one that's been
hovering will kick in. So this idea of hovering to some degree
can apply even by a שבועה, except by a נזיר when one
stops the other automatically kicks in here, you have to sort of,
because there is a terminal point to the first one. Here, it's
only retroactively you remove the first. That's a question? No, that's a
statement. לשנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, here's another version of the same discussion.
חיובא הוא דליכא, Chiyuva hu de-leka, it says you're not חייב chayav
only once if you take two שבועות. shvuot. השבועה איכא, Ha-shvuah ika,
but the שבועה is still to some degree present, the second one.
למאי הלכתא? Le-mai hilchata? For what implications? כי דרבא, Ki de-Rava, דאמר
רבא, de-amar Rava, נשאל על ראשונה חלה לו שנייה תחתיה. nish'al al
rishona, chala lo shniya tachteiha.
So if you remove the first one, the second one takes its
place. לימא מסייע ליה. Leima mesayia lei. Let me come and support
you with this. מי שנדר שתי נזירויות, Mi she-nadar shtei nezirot, we
did this yesterday, ומנה את הראשונה, u-manat et ha-rishona, person accepted two
נזירויות nezirot and counted the first one, והפריש קרבן, ve-hifrish korban, and
separated a קרבן, korban, ונשאל עליה, ve-nish'al aleha,
then got a היתר heter for the first נזירות. עלתה לו שנייה
בראשונה. Ala lo shniya bi-rishona. So the counting that you already did
counted for your second, for your second נזירות. Okay, your second one
retroactively kicked in and has been the one that's been in effect
for these last 30 days. Okay, so you see this is רבא's
Rava idea that retroactively you remove one and retroactively the second one,
the one that has not taken effect, will retroactively take
effect. So says no, כגון שקיבל עליו שתי נזירויות nezirot בבת אחת.
bat achat There, maybe it's a case like we said before where
you accepted two נזירויות nezirot at once. You said הרי עלי שתי
נזירויות היום. Harei alai shtei nezirot hayom. If you said that, right,
then we accept that since one didn't pre-exist, there's this idea that
they're both there, one is in effect and the other is hovering.
And if you remove the first one, retroactively the second kicks in.
But when they're sequential and you say שבועה שלא אוכל shvuah she'lo
ochal then you pause and you say שבועה שלא אוכל, shvuah she'lo
ochal, it could be we'll say the second statement meant nothing and
it's not like it created a שבועה that can't take effect and
if retroactively you remove the first one then the second one will.
Maybe I would say it did nothing. You already were מושבע, there
was no meaning to the second statement, zero. And that's so you
couldn't learn it out from the case of two נזירויות where there
is the idea of בבת אחת and there is the idea of
one hovering. Nevertheless, that's the assertion. Even by a שבועה where we
say אין שבועה חלה על שבועה, ein shvuah chala al shvuah, again,
we still focus on the idea of creating an obligation. A שבועה
is not just about שם שמים shem shamayim and lying or not
lying, it's about creating an obligation. So even by a שבועה and
אין שבועה חלה על שבועה, the second one somehow still hovers and
if retroactively you remove the first, the second one at least according
to רבא Rava can and will take effect. Yes?
That's something, I just think it's so fascinating. We've been using, you've
been using the language of hovering, but the גמרא actually, the גמרא
now is really using that language like there's a רווח, revach, there's
no space. So words are being conceptualized as physical objects that are
there, you know it's like those puzzles where you move the little
squares and there's no room for,
right, I'm not seeing the words as the object, I'm seeing the
obligations and the statuses that they are creating.
But the creative potential of language is so palpably concrete.
Right, I completely agree with that.
I mean, the foundation, what I say, a statement, it's just words
coming from my mind. How does that create anything in the world?
It comes very close to a material view of words. It's really
powerful.
I appreciate that. I mean, I don't know if I would say
the somehow the words are concretized, but the effect of the words
and I agree, I think that the power of מסכת נדרים, Masechet
Nedarim, you know, is it somehow... it by shows us almost tremendous
idea of what of what we create with our words. You create
a status of an object, right? Your words, the same way you
can make a קרבן Korban you can to some degree create your
own little religious world of making objects forbidden and you know sort
of drawing on this whole world of קרבנות, in a way that's
the גמרא that sort of speaks about נדרים Nedarim like making a
במה Bama because it's sort of like a little bit of a
do-it-yourself piece of Judaism, right? So you have all of your pre-existing
obligations, but now you can create you know in the neutral space
like nowadays instead of נדרים Nedarim we have people accepting like all
these חומרות, Chumras, right? It's not enough what sort of the תורה
Torah lays out you have to create your own area where you're
going to create איסורים. And then moving away from the religious phenomenon
per se, yes, it's about you know your words creating these realities
you know in the world, these obligations, these statuses and then you
know and they become these things that are taking effect and competing
and so on, absolutely, yep. It's a very powerful מסכת. Masechet. Okay,
let's take a look now at the next, turn the עמוד, next
משנה.
And people will be very I think gratified with this משנה because
a question that everybody has been asking is: What do you mean
what does this statement mean when we're dealing with ידות Yads and
כינויים? Kinuim? Why not just ask the guy what he meant, right?
Remember that question you've all been asking? So that question comes up
here basically addressed in this משנה. So let's take a look. סתם
נדרים להחמיר ופירושם להקל. Stam nedarim l'hachmir u'peirusham l'hakel.
So a סתם נדר Stam neder if we don't know what it
means, we will give it the more strict meaning. Okay, we've said
this before, but we will allow for its interpretation to be lenient
if somebody wants to say they meant something else then we will
accept that interpretation. Okay, so let's take a look. כיצד? Keitzad? What's
the example? אמר, Amar, הרי עלי כבשר מליח כיין נסך. Harei alai
k'basar maliach k'yayin nesech.
This should be forbidden to me or this should be to me
like
salted meat or
wine of libation. So what do you mean? אם בשל שלמים Im
b'shel shelamim or some have בשל שמים b'shel shamayim נדר, if you
mean like a קרבן, Korban, because you know although יין נסך yayin
nesech from a halakhic standpoint it means wine made as a libation
to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and just means wine as a libation.
Well you make wine as a libation to God, you know what
we bring with the קרבנות something called נסכים, nesachim, which is יין
נסך. yayin nesech. יין Yayin that is that you are מנסך menaseach
that you you know you
pour on the altar, right?
So therefore, when you say this is like wine of libation or
salted meat, for some reason salted meat is understood to mean a
meat as a sacrifice because כל קרבן חובתך תקריב מלח, kol korban
chovatcha takriv melach, so there was an idea of putting salt on
the meat. So it's understood that you mean sacrificial meat and wine.
So if somebody said let this be on me like sacrificial meat
and wine. Okay, sacrifice to whom? So אם בשל שלמים im b'shel
shelamim or בשל שמים b'shel shamayim נדר, if you mean sacrifice to
God, אסור. assur Then it's forbidden because that's a דבר הנדור, d'var
hanadur, something becomes sanctified because of your words. אם בשל עבודת כוכבים
נדר, Im b'shel avodat kochavim nadar, but if you meant sacrificial meat
and wine to an idol, although that's obviously very prohibited, but then
מותר, mutar, it's permissible because it's an idol is not a דבר
הנדור, d'var hanadur, right? Animals things that are sacrificed to idols are
forbidden but they're not forbidden because of your words and therefore you
cannot use them to make something forbidden. ואם סתם V'im satam or
ואם סתם, v'im stam,
and if you say if you don't explain what you mean, אסור
assur. we will give it the more strict translation. Okay, so this
is סתמם להחמיר. stamam l'hachmir. If somebody just said let this be
on me like sacrificial wine, it could mean one of two things.
One way if it means one thing it's מותר, mutar, means another
thing it's אסור. assur We will explain it to the to have
to give it the אסור assur meaning if there's no other thing
to go by. That's what סתמם להחמיר stamam l'hachmir means. However, פירושם
להקל peirusham l'hakel presumably means that if he tells us what I
meant was idolatrous libations and sacrifices, then we'll say okay, then it's
permissible. We will there are other what the משנה is telling us
is there are two possible interpretations, a strict one and a lenient
one. If we know nothing else we'll interpret it with the strict
one. But implicitly we will accept his his
you know his his clarification, right, that he meant a different one
and if he tells us he meant the lenient one then that
actually will be binding. Now, the ר"ן also says and תוספות Tosfot
discusses it, תוספות Tosfot or someone discusses, what if he says, you
know what? I didn't have one or the other in mind. I
heard my friend say it, it sounded good to me. Or I
just had in mind whatever this statement mean you know however this
statement whatever this statement usually means, that's what I meant. I wasn't
in particular thinking one or the other. I didn't realize so in
that case we'll give it the strict meaning as well.
Isn't it supposed to be invalid because he had no intention?
Oh, that's a good question. Maybe and he maybe he meant I
meant to make this thing אסור assur but what I meant by
the words sacrificial meat, you're right. Like let's say he said yes
I did make to mean to make this thing forbidden, but what
did I mean what type of sacrificial meat that I had no
idea I just heard people using this term or something like that,
right? But that's a good point too. Right, it sounds like the
פירושם peirusham is not Whether you were trying to create the איסור,
but what you meant by the words. When we say you have
to intend, it's not necessarily intend I think the specific meaning of
the words as much as intend to create the status. Okay, but
that's a very good point. Like that comes up a question all
the time, like somebody's doing ספירת העומר Sefirat HaOmer and they don't
really know how to speak Hebrew. So they read the Hebrew, I
mean they don't know how, they don't understand Hebrew they know how
to read it. So they read the Hebrew and they know today
is 37 and they say היום שבעה ושלושים יום hayom shivah ushloshim
yom whatever they read it, they don't know what any of the
one words means but they know what the whole sentence means, right?
Does that, is that a good act of counting? Right? There's interesting
questions, right? But you know what you're getting at but you don't
know what the words anyway. So yes, when we say you need
פיו ולבו שוין piv velibbo shavin it's primarily that you wanted to
create that status. But that's a very good point. Okay, so סתם
להחמיר stam lehachmir are two scenarios. One scenario is he walks away
and we're not around to ask him and he made this אסור
assur, on everybody. He says let this loaf of bread to be
like every to everybody in the world like sacrificial meat. And then
he goes away to Hawaii, whatever. Okay, so what do we say?
Yes or no? So then we say סתם להחמיר stam lehachmir we'll
give the stricter meaning. The other possibility of סתם להחמיר stam lehachmir
is we did ask him and we said what did you mean
by it? And he says I don't know, I guess meant sacrificial
meat. Well you know there's two very different types of sacrificial meat.
Oh I wasn't thinking about that. Okay? So then also we would
say סתם להחמיר. stam lehachmir. So he we're not around to ask
him or he doesn't really have anything to contribute to the conversation,
we say it means the strict meaning. If however he clarifies and
gives the more lenient meaning then we will accept his clarification. And
that's פירושו להקל. perusho lehakel. Okay?
Similarly if he says
הרי עלי כחרם harei alai kecherem let this be like חרם, cherem,
something like banned, okay?
Sanctified slash banned. So there are two types of חרם. cherem. One
goes to כהנים kohanim and they're allowed to benefit from it. And
one goes to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So אם כחרם של
שמים im kecherem shel shamayim if it's for the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash אסור, assur, it's forbidden, that's a דבר הנדור davar hanadur that's
forbidden to people. ואם כחרם של כהנים ve'im kecherem shel kohanim if
it's for the כהנים's kohanim חרם cherem then מותר, mutar, then it's
permissible because that's not forbidden to people, certainly not to the כהנים.
kohanim. ואם סתם ve'im stam if he doesn't clarify אסור, assur, it's
forbidden, we give it the more strict
interpretation. הרי עלי כמעשר harei alai kema'aser let this be on me
like the tithes. אם כמעשר בהמה נדר im kema'aser behemah nadar if
he meant like the מעשר ma'aser of animals אסור, assur that's forbidden
because you make מעשר ma'aser by animals by separating them out and
by designating them. I'll talk about that in a minute. ואם של
גורן ve'im shel goren מותר. mutar. If however it is the מעשר
ma'aser of the grain that's permissible. Why? Because even though that's a
דבר הנדור davar hanadur it's not a דבר האסור. davar ha'assur. Right?
A מעשר ma'aser is something that people are allowed to eat. So
that's not a problematic status. So that's right, a מעשר בהמה ma'aser
behemah is a קרבן. korban. It's not only a דבר הנדור davar
hanadur but it's forbidden. Whereas מעשר ma'aser of grain is is מותר
mutar and therefore it is not it's therefore it would not create
a נדר. ואם סתם ve'im stam and if he's not clear or
he doesn't clarify אסור assur we give it the strict interpretation. הרי
עלי כתרומה harei alai kiterumah let this be like תרומה. terumah. אם
כתרומת הלשכה im kiterumat halishkah if it's like the donation to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right the annual donation of the מחצית השקל
machatzit hashekel to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash נדר then אסור assur
it's forbidden. ואם של גורן ve'im shel goren if it's the תרומה
terumah of the grain of the threshing floor מותר mutar it's permissible.
We've discussed this before why תרומה terumah is not a דבר הנדור
davar hanadur either because it's not forbidden probably just simply because it's
not forbidden to all, it's only forbidden to non-כהנים. kohanim. I mentioned
to you also רמב"ם's Rambam idea that it's not a דבר הנדור
davar hanadur because it's not a free will type of a thing.
But anyway תרומה terumah is not considered a דבר הנדור davar hanadur
for נדר but תרומת הלשכה terumat halishkah is, it's forbidden to all
and it's given over to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So if
he meant one it's okay, one it's no good. ואם סתם ve'im
stam and if he was not and if he was unclarified אסור
asur. it's forbidden. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That last statement
is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because there's something to talk about in
terms of the last statement. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it matters where you did it. סתם תרומה
ביהודה אסורה stam terumah bi'Yehudah asurah in יהודה Yehudah it's forbidden because
תרומה terumah can mean תרומת הלשכה terumat halishkah and we give it
the stricter meaning. בגליל ba'Galil however in the Galilee מותר. mutar. Why?
שאין אנשי גליל מכירים את תרומת הלשכה she'ein anshei Galil makirim et
terumat halishkah
because people in the Galilee are not so familiar with the תרומת
הלשכה, terumat halishkah, right? They don't have a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
around. Now presumably everybody was supposed to give to the תרומת הלשכה,
terumat halishkah, right? That was a מחצית השקל machatzit hashekel and so
on. But it's not in their like it's not in their consciousness.
And therefore now you could say therefore it's a very unlikely meaning
of the term and therefore if it's not when we say סתם
להחמיר stam lehachmir it has to be when it's like you know
when it's at least as equally of likely of a meaning. That's
one possibility. The other which is maybe a variation of the same
is when they want to say תרומת הלשכה terumat halishkah they say
תרומת הלשכה. terumat halishkah. They don't just say the word תרומה. terumah.
They right for them תרומה terumah always means normal תרומה. terumah. תרומת
הלשכה terumat halishkah they would have the modifier. Right this always becomes
the interesting thing about what becomes the default and what needs the
modifier. Like you know it used to be when digital watch. It
used to be when digital watches came out, they were digital watches,
right? Now you talk about analog watches, which is funny because I
think very few people wear digital watches these days. But somehow, I
guess maybe because on your computer and on your iPhone or whatever,
anyway, like the question is right now, it used to be like
about email. Now if you want to send you're going to send
somebody something by mail, you'll say I'll send it to you by
snail mail, right? So which becomes like the default and which one
like needs the modifier? It's always a good question. There was this
very funny what's it
called? Daily Show
where Jon Stewart was doing a whole thing, I don't know, there
was some
something about
Chicago dissing New York about, I don't know, tallest building. I forget
what it was. Anyway, he was talking about Chicago they have this
deep dish pizza, right? So he says you know you have to
say you got this deep dish pizza. This is how he says
it, he takes up like a slice of pizza he says, you
know what we call this? Pizza. So you know
like what's the סתם stam and what has to be מפורש. meforash.
Anyway, so
if in גליל Galil when they say תרומה, Terumah, they mean תרומה.
Terumah. If they want to say תרומת הלשכה, Terumat HaLishkah, they'll modify
it, they'll say תרומת הלשכה. Terumat HaLishkah. So סתם תרומה stam Terumah
by there does not have the reasonable possible meaning in the גליל
Galil of תרומת הלשכה, Terumat HaLishkah, so there we actually would say
סתם להקל stam lehakel according to this because that's not a possible,
a reasonable meaning of that. Okay, סתם חרמים ביהודה. Stam charamim biYehudah.
Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah goes on and says, similar by חרם,
cherem, סתם חרמים ביהודה מותרין, Stam charamim biYehudah mutarin, בגליל אסורין. baGalil
asurin. In גליל Galil it's אסור. asur. Why? שאין אנשי גליל מכירין
את חרמי כהנים. She'ein anshei Galil makirin et charmei kohanim. The same
idea. גליל Galil is more removed from the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
so they're less familiar with בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash ideas. So when
they say חרם, cherem, now of course חרם cherem also goes to
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but still the idea of חרמי כהנים,
charmei kohanim, giving something over to the כהנים kohanim and using the
word חרם cherem is something that maybe only occurs in places where
there are a lot of כהנים. kohanim. In the גליל, Galil, the
word of חרם cherem really only means חרמי מקדש charmei mikdash and
not חרמי כהנים. charmei kohanim. So in the גליל, Galil, when they
say חרם cherem it's להחמיר. lehachmir. Now, but here's the problem. Why
in יהודה, Yehudah, because חרם cherem can mean חרמי כהנים, charmei kohanim,
is it מותרין? mutarin? Okay, in יהודה, Yehudah, חרם cherem can mean
חרמי כהנים, charmei kohanim, but it can also mean חרם המקדש, cherem
haMikdash, right?
I understand. So it could mean חרמי כהנים, charmei kohanim, but it
could also mean חרם המקדש. cherem haMikdash. Why doesn't that go back
to the principle of סתם נדרים להחמיר? stam nedarim lehachmir? Right? If,
if the איסור word is off the radar, like the word of
תרומת הלשכה Terumat HaLishkah in גליל Galil is off the radar, so
we're going to give it the lenient meaning. תרומה Terumah means
תרומת גורן terumat goren and it's מותר. mutar. But in the reverse
case, it's the... in יהודה, Yehudah, in גליל, Galil, the היתר heter
word is off the radar, חרמי כהנים, charmei kohanim, so fine, it's
אסור. asur. But in יהודה, Yehudah, both words are on the radar,
חרמי כהנים charmei kohanim and חרמי מקדש. charmei mikdash. So it should
also be אסור.
It's not logical, it's just a sociological reality.
I understand, but it's not that it doesn't mean חרמי מקדש charmei
mikdash in יהודה. Yehudah. It means it could mean both. If it
could mean both, then it should be להחמיר. lehachmir. So the גמרא
is going to ask that at the end. Why at the end
they're both not לחומרא? lechumra? But anyway, at least רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says that under... רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says under some circumstances
certain words are not part of the possible meaning of that last
word. Okay, so I guess we will end with here for now.
Yeah.
We have four examples.